<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>WSL on Alejandro Inglés Martínez</title><link>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/tags/wsl/</link><description>Recent content in WSL on Alejandro Inglés Martínez</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/tags/wsl/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Web service deployment with EC2 AWS</title><link>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/aws-ec2-assb/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/aws-ec2-assb/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/aws-ec2-assb/aws-ec2.png" alt="Featured image of post Web service deployment with EC2 AWS" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This project was developed for a Systems Architectures and Distributed Systems (ASSB) assignment during my fourth year of undergraduate studies. The main objective was to deploy a functional web service in a cloud environment using &lt;strong&gt;AWS&lt;/strong&gt; services, staying within the limits of the free plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The deployed web service consists of a load balancer that distributes requests between two EC2 instances, each with its own Apache server and web page.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main tasks performed included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Controlling and creating cost alerts&lt;/strong&gt;: Setting up alerts in AWS to ensure that all operations conformed to the free plan, avoiding unwanted additional charges.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deployment of EC2 instances&lt;/strong&gt;: Raise two instances of &lt;strong&gt;EC2&lt;/strong&gt; and connect to them via &lt;strong&gt;SSH&lt;/strong&gt;. On each of the instances, install the &lt;strong&gt;Apache&lt;/strong&gt; web server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Configuring Apache web servers&lt;/strong&gt;: Configuring the Apache services on both instances to serve a static web page created by myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deployment of a load balancer&lt;/strong&gt;: Deployment of a load balancer on AWS to evenly distribute incoming requests between the two Apache servers, optimising the load and ensuring higher availability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="../../post/aws-ec2-assb/assb-aes-ec2.pdf" &gt;&lt;strong&gt;View memory in pdf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Parallel computing in distributed systems with MPI.</title><link>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/mpi-assb/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/mpi-assb/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/mpi-assb/mpi-logo.png" alt="Featured image of post Parallel computing in distributed systems with MPI." /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This project was developed for the course Architecture of Systems and Software Basis (ASSB), during my fourth year of studies. The main objective was to become familiar with parallel programming on distributed memory computers using the &lt;strong&gt;MPI&lt;/strong&gt; library in &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt; (Message-Passing Interface). A widely used technique for distributed computing on multiple machines, commonly used in high performance clusters. In the case of this project everything was executed in my own computer, understanding my computer as a kind of cluster and its different cores as machines that form it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main tasks of this project are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Development of the ‘Hello World’ program with MPI&lt;/strong&gt;: As a first step, I programmed a basic program so that &lt;strong&gt;each process would print a message with its rank and the name of the processor it was running on&lt;/strong&gt;. In addition, I experimented with the possibility of launching more processes than the number of physical cores available, observing how MPI handles this scenario even though it loses performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scalar product of vectors in parallel&lt;/strong&gt;: I implemented a program with MPI that &lt;strong&gt;computes the scalar product of two large vectors&lt;/strong&gt;, distributing the work among several processes. Each process calculated a part of the scalar product, and then the results were brought together in the process of rank 0, which displayed the total result. A runtime measurement was also added, allowing analysis of how performance varied as the number of processes changed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Solving integrals using the trapezoid method&lt;/strong&gt;: I then &lt;strong&gt;implemented a program to calculate integrals using the trapezoid method&lt;/strong&gt;, parallelising the program so that each process calculated the sum of the trapezoids in a specific sub-interval. As before, the process at rank 0 was responsible for summing the results of all the processes and displaying the final value of the integral.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Performance and scalability analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: To evaluate the performance of the parallel program, I measured execution times and speedup when using different numbers of processes, from 1 to more than twice the number of available physical cores. The results were visualised in graphs showing how speedup improved as the number of processes increased, but also how efficiency decreased at certain points due to overhead in inter-process communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project documentation: &lt;a class="link" href="../../post/paralelizacion-mpi-assb/ASSB-mpi.pdf" &gt;&lt;strong&gt;View documentation in pdf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Parallel computing on multicore processors with OpenMP.</title><link>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/openmp-assb/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/openmp-assb/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/openmp-assb/openmp-logo.png" alt="Featured image of post Parallel computing on multicore processors with OpenMP." /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This project was developed during the Systems and Software Architecture and Basis (ASSB) course during my fourth year of studies. The main objective was to implement an algorithm for calculating the Pi number using the MonteCarlo method by programming in C both sequentially and using parallel programming techniques to take full advantage of the resources of multicore processors using the OpenMP library, which allows code to be executed in multiple threads efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main tasks performed were the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Development of the sequential and parallel version of the algorithm&lt;/strong&gt;: I implemented a program that simulates the throwing of random ‘darts’ inside a square inscribed in a circle. The ratio between the hits inside the circle and the total throws is used to calculate the value of Pi. In the parallel version, I used OpenMP to divide the work among several threads, taking full advantage of the resources of multi-core processors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time measurements and performance analysis&lt;/strong&gt;: After developing the two versions of the program, I performed time measurements to evaluate the performance of the parallel version compared to the sequential version. I used different thread configurations, from a single thread to more than twice the physical cores of the processor, in order to analyse the speedup and scalability of the algorithm. The speedup was calculated as the ratio between the single-threaded execution time and the multi-threaded execution time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Optimisation and management of shared resources&lt;/strong&gt;: During development, it was necessary to solve common problems in parallel programming, such as race conditions. In this case, I used OpenMP directives to define private variables on a per-thread basis, preventing multiple threads from simultaneously accessing the same global variables and affecting the final result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generating performance graphs&lt;/strong&gt;: After collecting runtime and speedup data, I generated graphs to visualise the performance of the program as the number of threads increased. These graphs demonstrated how the application scaled with increased thread count, highlighting the advantages and limitations of parallelisation in a shared-memory environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project documentation: &lt;a class="link" href="../../post/paralelizacion-openmp-assb/ASSB-openmp.pdf" &gt;&lt;strong&gt;View documentation in pdf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Client-Server Architecture in Java using TLS</title><link>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/security-gasca/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/security-gasca/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/security-gasca/java3.png" alt="Featured image of post Client-Server Architecture in Java using TLS" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This project was developed during the Security, Confidentiality and Identity Management (SCGI) course during my third year. This project focused on the design and development of a secure client-server architecture using the Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocol, with the aim of ensuring the confidentiality, integrity and authenticity of communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="context-and-objective"&gt;Context and Objective
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The project arose from the need to secure communications in an application that allows the transmission of sensitive data, such as user credentials (login/password), between clients and a central server. This type of application is especially relevant in environments where data privacy is crucial, such as the health sector, banking and any system where users must authenticate their identity to access services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="configuring-keystores-and-truststores"&gt;Configuring KeyStores and TrustStores
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;To implement TLS security, it was necessary to configure both the KeyStore and the TrustStore. These elements allow mutual authentication between the client and the server. The KeyStore contains the private keys and associated certificates that identify the entity (client or server), while the TrustStore manages the certificates of the trusted entities, allowing validation that the communication partners are legitimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the development of this project, Keytool, a tool included in the &lt;strong&gt;Java&lt;/strong&gt; JDK, was used to create and manage the certificates. The process required the configuration of environment variables such as JAVA_HOME and PATH, to facilitate the use of this tool from the command line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="implementation-of-tls-sockets"&gt;Implementation of TLS Sockets
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The communication between the client and the server was done through SSL (Secure Sockets Layer) sockets, over which the TLS protocol was integrated. At both ends, client and server, secure sockets were configured to allow the transmission of encrypted data. The server was designed to listen for incoming connections on a specific port (in this case, port 3343), authenticating clients by verifying their credentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLS Server&lt;/strong&gt;: The server was responsible for receiving client connections and authenticating each user by verifying their credentials (username and password). It also provided responses based on the result of this verification, informing the client whether the authentication was successful or unsuccessful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TLS client&lt;/strong&gt;: The client established a secure connection to the server and sent the user&amp;rsquo;s credentials for verification. The server&amp;rsquo;s response was displayed in a simple user interface, indicating whether the authentication process was successful or if there was an error.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="communication-and-security-testing"&gt;Communication and security testing
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Both secured and unsecured communication tests were conducted in order to highlight the importance of using TLS in applications that handle sensitive information. For the unsecured tests, an unencrypted socket was implemented to observe how an attacker, using tools such as &lt;strong&gt;Wireshark&lt;/strong&gt;, could capture and display in clear text the transmitted user credentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast, by enabling TLS, it was observed that all transmitted data was encrypted, making it impossible for an attacker to read the captured data on the network. This demonstrated the effectiveness of TLS in protecting the confidentiality and integrity of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="performance-and-concurrency"&gt;Performance and Concurrency
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;A key aspect of this project was the validation of system performance, specifically the ability to handle multiple concurrent connections. The server was configured to handle up to 300 concurrent connections, which was achieved by using Java threads to handle parallel requests. Although connections were made sequentially in the initial tests (one every second), the system proved to be robust in processing requests efficiently without compromising security or stability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project documentation: &lt;a class="link" href="../../post/seguridad-gasca/conexion_TLS.pdf" &gt;&lt;strong&gt;View documentation in pdf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>