<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>EC2 on Alejandro Inglés Martínez</title><link>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/tags/ec2/</link><description>Recent content in EC2 on Alejandro Inglés Martínez</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/tags/ec2/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Web service deployment with EC2 AWS</title><link>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/aws-ec2-assb/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/aws-ec2-assb/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/aws-ec2-assb/aws-ec2.png" alt="Featured image of post Web service deployment with EC2 AWS" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This project was developed for a Systems Architectures and Distributed Systems (ASSB) assignment during my fourth year of undergraduate studies. The main objective was to deploy a functional web service in a cloud environment using &lt;strong&gt;AWS&lt;/strong&gt; services, staying within the limits of the free plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The deployed web service consists of a load balancer that distributes requests between two EC2 instances, each with its own Apache server and web page.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main tasks performed included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Controlling and creating cost alerts&lt;/strong&gt;: Setting up alerts in AWS to ensure that all operations conformed to the free plan, avoiding unwanted additional charges.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deployment of EC2 instances&lt;/strong&gt;: Raise two instances of &lt;strong&gt;EC2&lt;/strong&gt; and connect to them via &lt;strong&gt;SSH&lt;/strong&gt;. On each of the instances, install the &lt;strong&gt;Apache&lt;/strong&gt; web server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Configuring Apache web servers&lt;/strong&gt;: Configuring the Apache services on both instances to serve a static web page created by myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deployment of a load balancer&lt;/strong&gt;: Deployment of a load balancer on AWS to evenly distribute incoming requests between the two Apache servers, optimising the load and ensuring higher availability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="../../post/aws-ec2-assb/assb-aes-ec2.pdf" &gt;&lt;strong&gt;View memory in pdf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>