<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Data Analysis on Alejandro Inglés Martínez</title><link>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/categories/data-analysis/</link><description>Recent content in Data Analysis on Alejandro Inglés Martínez</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/categories/data-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Datathon Andalucía Dedalus</title><link>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/datathon/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/datathon/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/datathon/dedalus-logo.png" alt="Featured image of post Datathon Andalucía Dedalus" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This project was developed during my third year of career for the Datathon organized by Dedalus and AWS in Andalusia, in collaboration with two fellow students. The main objective of this datathon was to work with a dataset provided on patients admitted to Intensive Care Units (ICU), to extract clinical value through cohort analysis and the creation of predictive models. The aim of this competition was to generate relevant information to improve hospital efficiency and optimize decision making in clinical contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="cohort-analysis"&gt;Cohort analysis
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Cohort analysis was one of the fundamental pillars of the project, as it allowed us to identify key patterns among hospitalized patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We performed a &lt;strong&gt;specific analysis on patients with cardiovascular problems&lt;/strong&gt;. This analysis included several important aspects:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The percentage of cases according to gender, which helped us to identify possible differences in the prevalence of cardiovascular problems between men and women.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The distribution of cases in relation to age, which allowed us to obtain a clear picture of the age groups most affected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number of cases according to body mass index (BMI), which provided a perspective on how BMI influences the incidence of these pathologies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The percentage of mortality according to BMI, revealing possible correlations between body weight and fatal outcomes in patients with cardiovascular problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We performed a &lt;strong&gt;more general cohort analysis&lt;/strong&gt; for all patients admitted to the ICU. This study included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The number of ICU admissions and discharges in different time slots, which provided information on the times of day when more admissions occurred.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The mortality rate of patients according to diagnosis, shedding light on which were the most critical pathologies in terms of survival.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The length of stay in ICU according to each diagnosis, which facilitated the identification of treatments and pathologies that required longer hospitalization time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="hospital-comparison"&gt;Hospital Comparison
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another highlight of the project was the comparative analysis between different hospitals. In this analysis, we evaluated the performance of hospitals in terms of their capacity to treat critical pathologies, using mortality as a key indicator. This analysis allowed us to compare the efficiency of hospitals in the treatment of certain diagnoses and pathologies, in addition to exploring the average length of stay in the ICU for each hospital. With this information, we were able to identify possible areas for improvement in hospital management and clinical care in different health centers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="predictive-models"&gt;Predictive Models
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;As part of the project, we also developed predictive models in order to anticipate behaviors and improve planning in ICUs. One of the main models was &lt;strong&gt;ICU congestion monitoring, which had the ability to predict when critical occupancy levels would be reached and thus anticipate potential bottlenecks in hospital care&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, we designed &lt;strong&gt;models that could predict the length of stay of patients in the ICU&lt;/strong&gt;, classifying them into short, medium or long stays. These predictive models not only allowed us to optimize hospital resource allocation, but also contributed to better discharge planning and reduced waiting times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="../../p/datathon/datathon-foto-grupo-sevilla.jpg"
width="615"
height="380"
srcset="../../p/datathon/datathon-foto-grupo-sevilla_hu_bc622d1e1b635cac.jpg 480w, ../../p/datathon/datathon-foto-grupo-sevilla_hu_1bec43cc8cdd2ed2.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Group photo"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="161"
data-flex-basis="388px"
&gt;&lt;img src="../../p/datathon/dedalus.jpg"
width="720"
height="675"
srcset="../../p/datathon/dedalus_hu_13600aa53aec4351.jpg 480w, ../../p/datathon/dedalus_hu_bee6ca3975e73dd4.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Photo during the presentation"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="106"
data-flex-basis="256px"
&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presentation: &lt;a class="link" href="../../post/datathon/ATENAS_Datathon_Dedalus.pdf" &gt;&lt;strong&gt;View presentation in pdf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Data project with Weka</title><link>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/weka-espacial/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/weka-espacial/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://aleingmar-pi-portfolio.pages.dev/p/weka-espacial/weka.png" alt="Featured image of post Data project with Weka" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;This project was developed as part of the Intelligent Systems (IS) course during my third year of studies. The work consisted of applying different classification and data pre-processing algorithms to solve a hypothetical problem about space travel in the distant future. The main objective was to predict, based on certain attributes of the passengers, whether they would be transported to an alternative dimension after a space accident.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="context-and-objective"&gt;Context and Objective
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The problem posed the situation where a spacecraft, with thousands of passengers on board, collides with a space-time anomaly, and half of the passengers are transported to another dimension. The challenge of the project was to develop a predictive model to identify which passengers would have been transported to that alternate dimension, based on attributes such as age, planet of origin, whether they were in cryo-sleep, and other factors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="data-preprocessing"&gt;Data Preprocessing
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The dataset provided contained information on approximately 8700 passengers, and consisted of 14 attributes, both numerical and nominal. Initially, certain variables considered irrelevant, such as passenger destination and amounts spent on luxury services, were removed. Next, missing value imputations were performed and categorical variables were binarised using One Hot Encoding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To improve the efficiency of distance-based ranking algorithms such as KNN, normalisation of numerical variables, in particular passenger age, was performed to ensure a fair comparison between the different attributes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="algorithms-implemented"&gt;Algorithms Implemented
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Several classification algorithms were tested, including:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ZeroR&lt;/strong&gt;: Used as a baseline, classifying all passengers based on the value of the most frequent class.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;J48&lt;/strong&gt;: A decision tree type algorithm that showed good results after a pruning process to avoid overfitting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KNN&lt;/strong&gt; (k-Nearest Neighbors): This classifier was based on the similarity between individuals to predict whether a passenger would be transported. Different values of K were tested, with 9 being the best performing value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Naive Bayes&lt;/strong&gt;: An algorithm that, despite its simplicity, provided good results by assuming independence between attributes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="results"&gt;Results
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The best performance was obtained using the KNN algorithm with a value of K=9, achieving an accuracy of 74.3%. In comparison, the other algorithms showed slightly lower performances. The experiments performed with &lt;strong&gt;cross-validation&lt;/strong&gt; helped to more reliably evaluate the models, ensuring that there was no over-fitting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project documentation: &lt;a class="link" href="../../post/weka-espacial/viaje-espacial-weka.pdf" &gt;&lt;strong&gt;View documentation in pdf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>